A Guide to the Papers of Henry Clay, 1798-1934, n.d.
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series I: Correspondence and Documents
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Jabez D. Hammond 1831 April 13, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Apr.15. #2529. (Box-folder 1:89)
    Clay encloses letters of introduction [not present]. He says that he regrets to learn of the "impracticability of Union among opponents of the Administration in New York. On that union I am well assured depends the vote of the State." He concludes by commenting on Andrew Jackson's declining support and says should "Mr. Calhoun be a Candidate it will prejudice the General."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence 1831 April 13, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Apr. 15. #5828, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:90)
    Clay replies to Lawrence's letter of March 29. Clay says that his willingness to retire from the Presidential race "was dictated by a thorough conviction of the evils brought and likely to be brought upon the Nation" by Jackson's "misrule; and an anxious desire to avert them from my Country. It was not dictated by any unwillingness on my part to encounter the perils of a canvass, nor fears as to its successful termination." He also says that his offer to step aside was not "prompted by any belief of my own that another's name could be advantageously substituted to mine." He closes with a postscript, asking Lawrence to share this letter with M.[atthew] L. Davis.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John Agg 1831 May 20, ALS, 2 pp. #1761. (Box-folder 1:91)
    Clay explains that Agg's recent letter was delayed. He comments on the upcoming elections and says that "whether we regard the goodness of the American System, or the present flattering prospects of its final triumph, by the overthrow of the existing feeble corrupt and incompetent Administration, the friends of that system have every motive for renewed and energetic assertion. He is sorry to hear of the financial difficulties of the Washington Daily National newspaper since "it has been decidedly the leading paper in supporting the principles of the Opposition." Clay concludes by stating that there is "every reason to count upon a most signal triumph at out approaching Elections in August."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to H.[ezekiah] Niles 1831 June 3, ALS, 2 pp.; docketed. #3920. (Box-folder 1:92)
    Clay responds to Niles's proposal to move the Niles' Register from Baltimore to New York. He says the move would be favorable and its "means of information and circulation would be greatly multiplied." In closing, Clay mentions the illness of Abraham H. Schenck and sends condolences to his brother Peter H. Schenck.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Richard Smith 1831 June 11, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Jun.31. #10751. (Box-folder 1:93)
    Clay has received Smith's letter in which a check for $121.51 was enclosed [not present]. Clay mentions a claim to dower and says that since he knows nothing of the "doweress" he "cannot judge the terms of a compromise."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Capt. John Meany 1831 June 14, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:94)
    Clay is unwilling "to hazard any conjecture" about the approaching elections but "will say that we shall be more than ever mortified if our friends do not return a large majority to the Legislature and to Congress."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1831 August 3, ALS, 3 pp.; with text on attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.5. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:95)
    Clay writes extensively about the "Antimasonic excitement," which he says "is likely to be troublesome." He has determined "not to mix myself in that controversy" and will not "make some declaration adverse to Masonry" as he has been urged to do. He "cannot admit the propriety of blending either Masonry or Anti Masonry with Federal Politics. What has the General Govt. to do with either? What part of the Constitution authorizes it to discountenance either? It has no more power to put down either than it has to interfere with any of the literary, benevolent or religious associations of the Country." Clay states that he does "not think we ought to be diverted by Anti Masonry" in the attempt to oust the Jackson administration. He closes by mentioning Charles Hammond and discussing the Baltimore Convention.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown 1831 August 24, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:96)
    Clay replies to Brown's letter of July 29th, which reached him "during my absence at the Olympian Springs." He comments on Mrs. Clay's health, the health of Brown's niece, and Brown's health. Clay thinks Brown's "advice, in respect to public life is good," and that if he "could devise a proper and honorable mode, of withdrawing my name from public notice, I would instantly do it." Clay reports that the recent elections in Kentucky resulted "in a majority for the Jackson party in Congress, and a majority to the opposition in the Legislature-a drawn battle." Clay mentions that he is planning to place his "son James in some Counting House at Philadelphia" and asks if Brown can assist him with any of his "mercantile acquaintances." He closes by stating that his "crops are fine, especially our great Staple, Corn. I am pleased with the occupation, and the prospect of the profits of farming; but Mrs. Clay's repugnance to the cares of a Country life may induce us, possibly, to go to town."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1831 August 26, ALS, 3 pp.; with separate address leaf; postmarked Lexington Aug.28. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:97)
    Clay acknowledges that "several of my prominent friends at Cincinnati were extremely discouraged by the issue of our Congressional elections, and were entertaining the project of substituting some other name to mine, as a Candidate for the Presidency." Clay states that he "should most cordially agree to such an arrangement, and even urge it, if such a substitute can be found with the approbation of our friends generally." He discusses the strengths needed by a candidate and says that "I am not an impartial if competent person to make this enquiry." He comments on the suggestion of John Marshall as a candidate and says he would be "delighted" to see Marshall as President instead of Jackson. He concludes that the party would be well served by waiting to see how events develop and says "we should not despair, certainly not of the Republic, if we do of our Candidate."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1831 October 9, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Oct.12. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:98)
    Clay comments on the "Anti Masonic nomination" of William Wirt which "has excited as much surprise at Lexington and with me as it has done at Cincinnati." Clay quotes from a letter from Josiah S. Johnston about the "Anti Masonic Convention" in Philadelphia, at which Wirt was nominated. Clay states that the National Republican Party should forbear "to attach Anti Masonry or Mr. Wirt" because the convention "may think it is politic to nominate him" and "it is prudent to the leave the door open to his party and him to unite with us."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1831 November 16, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Nov. 18, amended to Nov. 19. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:99)
    Clay says that he accepted a Senate seat only "from a sense of public duty and in conformity with the almost unanimous wishes of my friends. I go to my post however with not anticipations of pleasure from occupying it." Clay concludes by saying that if William Wirt and "Jackson should be the only Candidates, there will, I believe be concentration, but it will be on Jackson."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1831 December 18, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:100)
    Clay expresses regret for Brown's injuries and recommends postponement of his trip to New Orleans. Clay states that John Sergeant's nomination by the National Republican Party for Vice President "is thought here to have been the best that could have been made." Clay has seen John C. Calhoun "several times, but have had no political conversation with him." Clay does not believe Calhoun will be a candidate for the Presidency. If Andrew Jackson approves a bill to recharter the Bank of the United States, Clay says "it has been suggested that [Littleton W.] Tazewell will be brought out as the Southern Candidate for President."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Herring 1832 January 30, ALS, 1 p. #6273. (Box-folder 1:101)
    In response to Herring's inquiry, Clay states that "one of the best portraits of me" was made by the late Matthew Harris Jouett of Kentucky; Clay believes the portrait is "somewhere in the City of N. York" and formerly in the possession of Joseph Delaplaine. Clay has no portrait of himself in Washington which he can send to Herring.
  - Christian Hager, Woodford County, Versailles, Ky. to Henry Clay 1832 March 17, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf. #8557. (Box-folder 1:102)
    Hager asks Clay to see General [Walter] Jones and make some inquiry of him" concerning a lawsuit to be argued before the Court of Chancery next June. Hager states that "I hope you will be our next President it appears to me that Jacksons friends are many of them geting more Cooler what the[y] have been." Hager asks Clay to write about the status of the lawsuit and concludes with a postscript mentioning the unusually cold weather.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1832 March 28, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.29; with two receipts (each 1 p.) dated 1831 April 8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:103)
    Clay comments on Brown's health and tells him he is wise to abandon his trip to New Orleans. Clay reports that James Erwin was robbed in New Orleans of promissory notes worth $20,000. He concludes by declining an invitation to visit Philadelphia saying "whenever I go from my abode, I become a State prisoner, and I love liberty in name but more in fact."
  - Henry Clay to Gen. W.[alter] Jones 1832 April 7, ALS, 1 p. with attached address leaf. #8557. (Box-folder 1:104)
    Clay thanks Jones for his note and the "excellent cheese" from Mr. Palmer. Clay encloses a letter from Mr. Hager [see 1832 March 17, above] and asks Jones for any information which Clay will then communicate to Hager.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Brantz Mayer 1832 June 17, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jun.17. #4990. (Box-folder 1:105)
    Clay replies to Mayer's request for information to compile a biography of Daniel Boone. Clay "never personally knew Boone. When in 1797 I migrated to Kentucky, he had gone further West." Clay suggests that Mayer obtain the series of articles on the early history of Kentucky by John Bradford published in the Lexington Kentucky Gazette. He also mentions Gilbert Imlay's A topographical description of the western territory of North America and Humphrey Marshall's The history of Kentucky. "Neither of them is well written. The first is rare, and I really do not know where it can be procured. Imlay also wrote a bad novel, the title of which I do not recollect. Marshall's history may be easily obtained in K. possibly in some of the Atlantic book stores." Clay suggests that the "best repository of materials for your work is the family of Boone."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James F. Conover 1832 June 30, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Washington Jul.3. #4475. (Box-folder 1:106)
    Clay comments on the formation of an "Electoral ticket" by the "Anti Masonic party" in Ohio. He says there is much confidence that Pennsylvania will not support Jackson. He mentions the Tariff Bill and the Land Bill in the Senate and closes by saying he thinks Congress will not adjourn before the 16th.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John L. Lawrence 1832 September 6, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Sep. 6. #5828. (Box-folder 1:107)
    Clay comments on the defeat of Richard A. Buckner which he says "was very mortifying" as it "resulted entirely from religious prejudices." He states that the "other elections terminated very favorably" and the National Republicans have a majority in both houses of the Kentucky legislature. Clay comments on elections in Ohio, Indiana, Louisiana, Missouri and New York.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James F. Conover 1832 September 8, ALS, 2 pp.; with separate address leaf; docketed. #4475-a. (Box-folder 1:108)
    Clay extends regrets for Conover's "private affliction" and mentions the death of his mother-in-law, Susannah Gray Hart. He says that the "defeat of our Governor [Richard A. Buckner] was mortifying" but the other results of the election were gratifying. Clay comments on the division between the Anti Masons and National Republicans in Ohio. He continues to believe "that Jackson will be defeated" and regrets the "perseverance" of Judge John McLean in continuing to hope that he would be selected as a Presidential candidate.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Robert S. Rose 1832 September 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #1761. (Box-folder 1:109)
    Clay thanks Rose for his letter of recommendation for General Holsteen but regrets he does "not know of any place in this quarter, at present, which would be acceptable to him." Clay mentions that the University of Kentucky "has been laboring under difficulties from the loss by fire of the principal building." Clay mentions that he "had an opportunity of passing a short time in Virginia with Mr. [James] Madison and Govr. [James] Barbour. Mr. Madison is feeble in health but his mind and memory are perfectly sound." Clay concludes by saying he is glad to hear that New York is withdrawing support from Andrew Jackson.
  - Daniel Webster to Henry Clay 1832 October 22, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #6078-b. (Box-folder 1:109A)
    Webster says that the early returns from Pennsylvania were encouraging, but the later returns did not sustain the first impression. Webster says they were "thrown badly back by Ohio." But for that, Webster would "have had strong hopes of Maine & some hopes of N. Hamp." He believes that "the anti-Jackson ticket" will prevail in New York. Webster asks for news of Missouri and closes with regards to Mrs. Clay.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown 1832 October 23, ALS, 2 pp.; with attached blank leaf. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:110)
    Clay comments on a case Brown is appealing to the U.S. Supreme Court and promises to "take care of the case there for you." He mentions that his son Henry has married Julia Prather of Louisville. Clay attended the wedding and returned "slightly indisposed with an ordinary complaint." Because cholera has broken out in Louisville, Clay says "you may probably hear that I caught the pestilence, and have been long since dead and buried. You are authorized to contradict, most positively, such a report if you should hear it." Clay mentions the illness of Anne Clay Erwin's youngest child. He mentions the Kentucky elections and hopes that "the State will on friday week choose Anti Jackson Electors." Clay closes by suggesting that Brown abandon his plans for a trip to New Orleans "considering the prevalence of the Yellow fever there, with the prospect of its being followed by the Cholera."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to John J. Crittenden 1832 November 28, ALS, 1 p. #3121. (Box-folder 1:111)
    Clay comments that Crittenden's "views, in regard to your wishes on the subject of a service in the Senate, correspond with your character." Clay had planned to depart for Washington around Christmas "but the dread of a winters journey and the present good prospects of weather have induced me to proceed immediately."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to John L. Gilliland 1833 January 14, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Jan.16. #4602. (Box-folder 1:112)
    Clay thanks Gilliland for the "box containing the Specimens of your pressed glass ware. He tells Gilliland that the policy of tariff protection is "now in imminent danger," and that "the people alone can now save it." He concludes by saying he does not believe the recent election demonstrated popular opposition to public policy.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Dr. Morris 1833 March 2, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.4. #38-79. (Box-folder 1:113)
    Clay asks [James Maury] Morris if he wishes to sell his lot on Poydras Street in New Orleans and, if so, at what price.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to Augustus E. Cohen 1833 March 4, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Mar.7. #1761. (Box-folder 1:114)
    Clay replies to Cohen's letter and discusses the Compromise Tariff bill. He concludes by saying he does "not regard myself as a regular practitioner of the Law" and therefore, would not be able to have Cohen study under him.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to R.[ichard] H.[enry] Wilde 1833 April 27, ALS, 3 pp. #1754-b. (Box-folder 1:115)
    "Confidential" in Clay's hand following salutation. Clay discusses the Compromise Tariff bill and says that a "large section of the Jackson party, headed by Mr. V. Buren, will attempt either to impress the North with the belief that its interest were injuriously affected...or the South with the opinion that its interests were not sufficiently attended to." He then tells Wilde that "the danger you apprehend from a surplus Revenue will not be realized." Clay says that "passage of the Land Bill would have afforded further security, and I think most desirable security, against the extraordinary inconvenience of a superabundant exchequer." Clay will introduce a new land bill in the next session of Congress. Clay states that the "prospects of a renewal of the Charter of the U. States bank have decidedly improved" and he does "not despair of its being accomplished." Clay concludes by discussing the possibility of the emancipation of slaves in the British West Indies and says that the "danger is perhaps not sufficiently near or great to justify any interference from us." He says that slavery "lies at the bottom of many of the evils under which the Southern Atlantic States are suffering" and though Wilde has Constitutional grounds to protest "against the slightest interference of the Genl. Government with the institution of Slavery or the condition of its unfortunate subjects, it is perfectly manifest, I think, that you will have soon to alter materially the character of their labor. You will either have to find new products for it, or new markets for its present products."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to Dr. Morris 1833 May 19, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington May 21. #2483-a. (Box-folder 1:116)
    Clay will tell his friends of Morris' determination to sell his New Orleans lots at auction. In the lengthy postscript, Clay says that if "others have found pleasure in contemplating the political condition of our Country, for the last few years, it is more than you and I have."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown 1833 July 7, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Jul.8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:117)
    Clay mentions that a "few stragling cases of Cholera" continue in Lexington and that several families have lost slaves to the disease. Clay's son and daughter-in-law are expecting a child this month. The possibility of the emancipation of slaves in the British West Indies "will exert a moral influence on that institution in the U. States; but I do not apprehend any immediate effects from it" and does not believe emancipation will happen in the United States "in our time." Clay predicts that Southern slave owners will be "more sensitive to the slightest disturbance of the question." Northerners are "probably interested in the continuance of Southern slavery."
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to James Brown 1833 September 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf; docketed. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:118)
    Clay has heard from Dr. Nathaniel Chapman of Brown's "severe attack" but hopes his health is better now. He and Mrs. Clay will leave Lexington and "proceed directly to you in Philadelphia" as soon as Anne Clay Erwin "is confined, which is expected in eight or ten days."
  - Henry Clay, Baltimore, to James Brown 1833 October 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Lexington Oct. 8. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:119)
    Clay will be joined in Baltimore by Mrs. Clay, John Morrison Clay and Henry C. Duralde "the day after tomorrow." Clay is glad to hear that Brown's health is "almost entirely re-established." Clay concludes by announcing that his daughter "was delivered of a Son on the morning of the 2d. inst."
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to S.[amuel] Fleet 1833 December 4, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Dec.5. #2933-a. (Box-folder 1:120)
    Clay thanks Fleet for sending him "specimens of Sisal Hemp" and adds "they look well, but I am not sufficiently acquainted with its properties, culture or produce to determine whether it could be advantageously introduced into our agriculture." Clay compliments Fleet on his editorship of the New York Farmer, regrets that he is too busy to write for Fleet and asks how he can pay for a subscription.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Brown 1833 December 10, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; postmarked Washington Dec.11. #991, Tracy W. McGregor Library. (Box-folder 1:121)
    Clay is anxious to hear from Brown. The Clays have "taken a small furnished house in the rear of Gadsby's." Clay says there is an apparent majority in the House of Representatives for and in the Senate against the Jackson administration.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to James Barbour 1833 December 15, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf. #38-114. (Box-folder 1:122)
    Clay "met with Judge Bullard" of Louisiana and "had a conversation with him about your Florida slaves." Bullard "says that unless there is an unusual proportion of very young and old among them, they are worth $500 each; that the blacksmith if a tolerably good one and not old, is worth $1500-the rough carpenter $1200, women $500 each. Bullard will offer $20,000 for the slaves. Clay says Bullard would be glad to reach an arrangement with Barbour, "putting in 1250 acres of first rate Red River land at valuation (he has been offered $10 per acre) and the slaves at valuation, and working the whole together." Bullard says such an arrangement would produce 300 bales of cotton per year. Clay says that though cotton "has fallen to thirteen cents" he believes Barbour can count on $500 apiece for the slaves.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to George Watterson 1834 May 2, ALS, 1 p. #3417-b. (Box-folder 2:1)
    Clay acknowledges Watterson's election as an honorary member of the Columbian Horticultural Society of the District of Columbia.
  - Henry Clay, Washington, to John S. Wellford, John Coalter, John Tayloe Lomax 1834 May 30, ALS, 1 p.; with attached blank leaf. #3121. (Box-folder 2:2)
    Clay declines an invitation to attend the "Whig Celebration" in Fredericksburg, Va. Considerations of public duty have compelled him also to decline an invitation to a similar function in Alexandria, Va.
  - Henry Clay, Ashland, to B.[ellamy] Storer 1834 August 8, ALS, 1 p.; with attached address leaf; docketed; postmarked Lexington Aug.26. #2148. (Box-folder 2:3)